Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan and today we're
going to be learning about the tips
and tricks on how to convert a Haworth
projection to a Fischer projection
in introductory biochemistry.
Now one of the ways that you learn
all about how to show different
simple sugars or carbohydrates.
is by drawing a Fischer projection,
just like the one shown here, where
you might draw the enantiomers, you
might label all the chiral carbons,
the epimers, the diastereomers, whether
it's an ketose, he'll show reactions.
But as we realize that sugars do not
simply generally exist like this,
we always show them as, uh, these
different type of ring structures over
here, known as a Haworth projection.
Now, in most courses, they focus
on going from Fischer to Haworth,
but very rarely do they talk about,
well, how do you go backwards?
How do you disassemble it to be
able to label what sugar it is?
What is the easiest way to do this?
And that's what we're going
to show in this video.
is the little tips and tricks step
by step how to break down one of
these in a very quick and easy way.
We're going to go through two
different molecules to illustrate this.
So let's take a look at the different
steps and thank you so much for
stopping by and let's look at and try
to learn and conquer how to do this.
The first step that we're going to
be doing is we number our carbons
and the thing is when we are looking
at these rings We have to figure
out what the anomeric carbon is.
So whenever we are finding our
anomeric, we need to find what we
call a hemiacetal or a hemiketal.
So we're looking for a signature.
And whenever we're looking for
this, I always like to say we're
looking for the little set of googly
eyes that you see in the molecule.
So for example, if I kind of have one
of, uh, these little hemiacetals here,
you can kind of just imagine that has
two little eyeballs on it with some
little kind of little eyebrows above it.
And these are your eyeballs that are here.
You're looking for the two oxygens.
that are on these molecules and
they're both connected to the anomeric
carbon, which is right here as I'm
kind of showing here in purple.
Um, it's that little dot.
Those are your anomerics.
So if we go to the structure over here,
you want to try to give the anomeric
carbon the lowest number possible.
And what we can see here as well,
you can notice that we do have an
anomeric carbon where those two O's
are connecting to this single point.
So this is what we're going
to give the number one.
So we number around the ring.
So it goes one, two, three, four, five,
and we're going to number it as if it's a
chain, and continue the numbering outside.
So number six.
So one, two, three, four, five, and six.
Now other things that are really
important to to try to remember as
well is whether or not it's alpha
or beta because sometimes in your
course you might have to label that.
Now it's pretty
straightforward how to do it.
So if you kind of look at let's
say this OH here that I'm now
highlighting in teal and the CH5OH.
Notice how they're both together.
Together meaning same.
This is cis.
So in this case, if they're both
pointing up together or both pointing
down together, that's referring to cis.
So what we have here is a beta ring
structure because they are together.
If the OH was, let's say if it was
pointing on the other end, and if I
were to switch it, let's say I put
it here, and it was pointing down.
Now they're both opposite of each other.
This is referred to as alpha or trans.
In order to kind of remember
those, there's a little trick that
I learned that I kind of like.
If you kind of look at the alpha symbol
and I put like little dots going down
the side, notice how essentially the
little tails of the alpha are both
pointing in opposite directions.
That's how you can kind of remember trans.
Whereas with cis, the little,
notice how the two humps of
the B are together, right?
They both are together
like a little heart.
They go together, right?
Step two, we're going to draw
the Fischer projection backbone.
Now before we can do that, we have
to be able to label whether this
is an aldose, meaning an aldehyde,
or a ketose, meaning a ketone.
Now the way that we do this,
we look at the anomeric carbon
and we count where it was.
So if it's at number one, that
means that it's an aldehyde.
If it's at number two, it's a ketose.
Now when we numbered the structure
from earlier, we saw that at number
one, this is our anomeric carbon.
meaning that we're
going to have an aldose.
So what you're going to first
do is you're going to write
that you have an aldose here.
So you have C double bond O H and we're
going to write that on our structure.
Now the next thing is we're going
to draw our lines for our backbone.
So what I do is I just draw a little
spine here and you're going to end
it with the CH2OH which is on carbon
number six from our original structure.
Okay.
Now All the other spots
are your chiro caron.
So 2, 3, 4, and five are all chiro carons.
So you need to draw a little flat
line for each of these spots.
So we have 2, 3, 4, and then five.
Okay, so we have each of those spots.
One, two, let's number them as well.
So we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
and the last one is six.
Now the last thing is, before we move
on to our next step, is, depending on
where that CH2OH is, at number 6, if it's
pointing up or down, tells you where your
last chiral OH is, on carbon number 5.
So, if it was pointing up, that
means that it's a D enantiomer.
If it's pointing down, it's an L
in the antimer, which is really
important because that tells you,
hey, which direction it's going to be.
On our original structure, you can see
that the CH2OH here was pointing up.
So what that's going to let you know
is, hey, we're going to put this
going to the right on our structure.
So we have one of our pieces here.
Let's go into the next step to see a quick
and easy way to fill in the rest of this.
Step number three is what I consider a
pro tip being I've done so many of these
in my own personal teaching career.
The easiest way to do this is if
you draw a line down the bold part
of the Haworth projection, which
shows the wedge characteristic.
So, which is on the bottom here.
So what I do is whenever I'm visually
looking at these, I draw a little
imaginary line down the middle.
So if I do that here, so where this
little wedge is, I'm drawing these
little dots to kind of illustrate how
I'm going to be looking at the structure.
Now depending on where everything
is, you can actually quickly see how
to fill in your is your projection.
that is on the left here.
So what we're going to do is, is
once you write that line, we are
just going to turn it slightly.
So we're going to turn it just like this.
And what it's going to do, so I turned it.
back.
So I turned it 90 degrees to the left.
And what this is going to, this actually
shows you is where to put all your OHs.
So if we look at carbon number two, notice
how the OH is pointing to the right.
So that's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to write OH.
I'm going to put that
pointing to the right.
Okay.
So OH.
H.
Now on carbon number three, notice how
the OH is pointing to the left hand side.
So I'm going to put an
OH pointing to the left.
Now on carbon number four, it's on the
right hand side of my dotted line, so
we're going to fill that in as well.
Now we have our complete diagram.
structure.
Now if you're not able to turn that on
your own very easily, you can always
turn your paper or your notebook
just to kind of show how to do that.
Another easy way to do it is that if it's
on the upper side of the dotted line,
Is that upper means equals left, and if
it's down, that means that equals right.
Okay, when it comes to filling in
all these other chiral carbons.
Do not get it confused with carbon
number five, that one's different.
So let's try to identify which
molecule this is, which is the last
step is we're going to name and
identify our Fischer projection.
Our next step is that we're going to
name and identify what our structure is.
When you're trying to identify
these, it can be really complicated,
especially when you have a lot of
different molecules in front of you.
The first thing I would recommend
doing is classifying your structure,
meaning that we have an Aldo Hexoses,
so it's an aldehyde with six carbons.
And that will help you limit down
all the types of diastereomers and
nanotumors you're going to be looking at.
We have, we also know that we have
a beta, or in our case was a beta D
version of this structure as well.
You know, a cis in the beginning, and
our last OH group is going to the right.
So the quick way to look at this
structure is how to identify it, is
I look at one side of the molecule.
So in this case, what I'm looking
at is I see that I have OH, HOH.
Oh.
So I'm gonna match one side.
So when we're looking, we're
gonna try to find OH, HOH.
So if I look at, let's say like
looking at the first one, right?
Allo doesn't match.
Outros doesn't match.
Wait, that's H-O-H-O-H.
Now if I look at glucose,
that one is OH, HO, HOH.
So that is a quick way to kind of identify
like, hey, do you have the right one?
So you could also circle,
let's say the ohs as well,
and see like, okay, which one.
matches the same pattern.
So you're trying to figure out like,
okay, where is everything situated?
So what this tells us is the one that
we're working on is beta D glucose,
which is the name of our molecule.
Let's take a look at another
one to practice looking at
all these configurations
and putting it all together.
Okay, let's put it all together
going through our steps.
So here we have, I want you to draw
the Fischer projection and name it.
How would you do it?
So the first thing we said to do is we're
going to number our carbons and try to
give the anomeric the lowest one possible.
So once again, what we're going to do is
we're looking for our little eyeballs.
And what you can see here is
looking at the structure is right
here is that you have the two OHS.
Both kind of meeting here
at the exact same spot.
So what this tells you is that
here is your anomeric carbon, we'll
use a little star to tell us that.
Now one thing you'll notice
is that you don't want to just
automatically assume it's number one.
You gotta look if there's any
carbons that are currently next to
it, and we see that we have one.
So meaning that this one's a
ketose, it's starting at this point.
So what we'll do is we
number that number one.
We go in number two.
Number three number four and then we have
number five and we follow the carbons
around as if it's in a chain Right,
the ring is also can exist as a chain.
So you need to show both So we have
six carbons and it we notice that
starting at CH2OH So what we're going
to do is write CH2OH OH at the top.
Now being it's a carbon number
two, that's letting you know, hey,
we have a ketone in this case.
So we have C double bond O, and what
we're going to do is just to kind
of help illustrate that we'll keep
our numbering with the same colors.
So we got one, two.
Now at the very end of the chain, we
know it's CH2OH is our last piece.
Okay, so now we have all of our pieces.
We'll put in our chiral carbons.
We should have a total of six total.
So we have one, two,
three, four, five, six.
All right, now our last step was
putting that little dotted line in
place to determine where the OHs go.
So I'm going to put a little dots here
across the bottom to kind of help us
see the trend because we need to figure
out where does carbon three and four go.
on this molecule.
And the same thing with carbon number
5 as well, which was our last CH2OH.
So if we go in order, carbon
number 3 is going down, which means
that it's on the right hand side.
And if it helps to, we can turn the
molecule as well to help show that.
What we can see is that, okay, the first
OH is pointing to the right hand side.
On carbon number 4, it's pointing
towards the opposite, which is the left.
So let's do that here.
So we have, already have 3 filled in.
Okay.
Number four, we're going to put O, then H.
Now, carbon 5 depends on where
is the last CH2OH pointing.
Is it pointing up or down?
In this case, it's pointing down.
So that means that it's going
to be on the left hand side,
is where that's going to go.
So we are going to put that in.
So it's telling you, hey,
you have an L configuration.
in your molecule.
So let's kind of write that.
And we also have alpha as well.
So we have alpha, uh, alpha L.
And the way that I could tell if it's
alpha is we see we have one OH pointing
up, the other one pointing down.
So they're both opposite sides.
So let's try to name and
identify what we have.
So if I were to do this, the thing
is that's more common is more, most
monosaccharides tend to be given to
you as the D configuration, right?
In most reference sheets, they
are the more common because you
biologically tend to find L, or
sorry, D configuration in the body.
So, being that we have an L carbon
here, right, because the OH is on
the left, what we have to do is we
have to draw its mirror image first.
So if we were to do that, so let's
kind of make our little mirror here,
and what we're going to do is we're
going to copy this down, and flip all
of the chiral carbons in our molecule.
So we'll redraw this, just like,
redraw the backbone just like so.
Now we're going to fill in all of
our O H's, H's to mirror each other.
So what we have here is we have
O H, then O H, O H, and I'll fill
in all the hydrogens, H, H, H.
That way we have both the
L and the D configurations.
So we've got L, And then D.
All right, so on our D configuration,
what we need is we need OH left, we need
left, right, right for our configuration.
So if we were to look here, left,
right, right, what we can see really
quickly is that fructose matches
left, right, right here at the bottom.
So that's letting you know that, oh,
your structure that you have is fructose.
So to name our original molecule,
this is going to be alpha L.
Fructose is going to be the name of it.
So this is my, my tips and tricks on
how to do these, how to go backwards.
So hopefully this helped you a
little bit to see, like, just draw
a little line down the middle.
It makes it a lot faster to do it, right.
You can do it in just a few minutes.
Thank you for listening.
If this video did help you, please feel
free to share it, like it, uh, subscribe
to the channel for more introductory,
organic and biochemistry videos.
Thank you all and I hope
you have a wonderful day.
Bye now.